John Wills Greenslade Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
John Wills Greenslade Papers 1847-1961 (bulk 1895-1952)
MSS13235
Greenslade, John Wills, 1880-1950
2,870 items
11 containers plus 17 oversize
15.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Naval officer. Correspondence, diaries, memoranda, reports, speeches and writings, subject files, dispatches, contracts, blueprints, charts, maps, tables, scrapbooks, clippings, photographs, and other papers documenting Greenslade's career in the United States Navy from the Spanish-American War through both world wars.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Beck, William H. (William Hopkins), 1892-1957--Correspondence.; Bostwick, W. A.--Correspondence.; Brooks, Stanley Truman, 1902-1958--Correspondence.; Greenslade, John F. (John Francis), 1904- --Correspondence.; Greenslade, John Wills, 1880-1950.; Halstead, A. S. (Alexander Seaman), 1861-1923--Correspondence.; Horne, Frederick Joseph, 1880-1959--Correspondence.; Ingersoll, Royal E. (Royal Eason), 1883-1976--Correspondence.; King, Ernest Joseph, 1878-1956--Correspondence.; Knox, Frank, 1874-1944--Correspondence.; Leahy, William D.--Correspondence.; Leigh, Richard H. (Richard Henry), 1870-1946--Correspondence.; Lethem, Gordon J.--Correspondence.; Lothian, Philip Henry Kerr, Marquis of, 1882-1940--Correspondence.; Nimitz, Chester W. (Chester William), 1885-1966--Correspondence.; Pott, Herbert, approximately 1886-1945--Correspondence.; Reber, John, 1887-1960--Correspondence.; Slavich, John F.--Correspondence.; Taussig, Joseph K. (Joseph Knefler), 1877-1947--Correspondence.; Taylor, J. Frank--Correspondence.; Warren, Earl, 1891-1974--Correspondence.; Windsor, Edward, Duke of, 1894-1972--Correspondence.
Organizations
Naval War College (U.S.); United States Naval Academy.--Faculty.; United States. Navy--Officers.; United States. Navy--Submarine forces.; United States. Navy. Office of the Commander of the Western Sea Frontier.
Subjects
Military bases, American.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Naval operations, American.; Submarine mines.; Submarines (Ships); World War, 1914-1918--Campaigns--North Sea.; World War, 1914-1918--Naval operations, American.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations, American.
Places
Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain.
Occupations
Naval officers.
Provenance
The papers of John Wills Greenslade, naval officer, were deposited in the Library of Congress by the Naval Historical Foundation in 1968 and 1977. The deposit was converted to a gift in 1998.
Transfers
Items have been transferred from the Manuscript Division to other custodial divisions of the Library. Some photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division. Sound recordings have been transferred to the Motion Picture, Broadcasting, and Recorded Sound Division. All transfers are identified in these divisions as part of the John Wills Greenslade Papers in the Naval Historical Foundation Collection.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of John Wills Greenslade are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1880, Jan. 11 Born, Bellevue, Ohio
1898 Served on the Chicago (protected cruiser), Cuban campaign, and the Montgomery (cruiser), Puerto Rican campaign, Spanish-American War
1899 Graduated United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1899 1902 Served in Philippines
1904 Married Marie Melanie Taylor (died 1936)
1904 1906 Instructor, electrical engineering, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1909 1911 Instructor, electrical engineering, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1914 Commanded Vulcan (collier)
1915 1916 Senior Assistant to Head, Department of Electrical Engineering, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1917 Head, Department of Ordinance and Gunnery, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md.
1918 Commissioned captain; commanded Housatonic (mine layer), Northern Mine Barrage, North Sea
1919 Commanded Galveston (cruiser)
1920 1923 Inspector of ordinance, Naval Powder Factory and Proving Ground, Indian Head, Md.
1923 1925 Commanded Mine Squadron I, United States Fleet
1926 1928 Head, Operations Department, Naval War College, Newport, R.I.
1928 1929 Commanded Pennsylvania (battleship)
1929 1930 Chief of staff, Battleship Divisions, United States Fleet
1932 Commissioned rear admiral
1932 1934 Commanded Submarine Force, United States Fleet
1933 1939 Vice admiral, commander battleships, United States Fleet
1937 Married Mary Lee Gallagher (died 1943)
1940 1941 Senior member, President's Board to Select Sites of Bases in British Possessions
1941 1944 Commandant, Twelfth Naval District with additional duty as Commandant, Pacific Southern Naval Coastal Frontier
1944 Retired from navy Coordinator, naval logistics, Pacific Coast Chair, joint boards for ship operations, building and repair, Pacific Coast Married Alma Rudd Gunther
1945 Resources coordinator, Western Sea Frontier
1950, Jan. 6 Died, Bellevue, Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The papers of John Wills Greenslade (1880-1950) span the years 1847-1961, with the bulk of the items concentrated in the period 1895-1952. The collection contains correspondence, writings, memoranda, printed matter, photographs, scrapbooks, and other material documenting Greenslade's career as a naval officer from the Spanish-American War through World War II, notably during the North Sea mine barrage, 1917-1918; as chief of staff, Battleships Division, 1929-1930; commander, Submarine Force, 1932-1934; as senior member of the President's Board to Select Base Sites in British Possessions, 1940-1941; and as commander of the Western fleet from 1942 to 1944. The papers are arranged into the following series: Diaries, Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Subject File, Miscellany, and Oversize.
The Diaries contain originals and copies of letters from Greenslade to his mother, Nell Wills Greenslade, and sister, Sophia J. Greenslade, from the United States Naval Academy and subsequent voyages, including duty in the Philippines aboard the gunboat Concord, 1895-1900; the log of the cruiser Chicago, 1899-1901, the gunboat Princeton, and others, 1901-1904; and diaries of the cruise of the collier Vulcan in 1914; personal and private diary from the mine layer Housatonic, 1918; and notes from his trip to Baku aboard the destroyer Cole, 1919-1920. Further material on the Housatonic is in the Subject File under North Sea mine barrage and in a photograph album in the Miscellany.
Correspondence includes administrative and general correspondence as well as letters of congratulation and sympathy. Correspondents include W. A. Bostwick, A. S. Halstead, Frederick J. ("Fritz") Horne, Royal E. Ingersoll, Ernest Joseph King, Frank Knox, William D. Leahy, Richard H. Leigh, Chester W. Nimitz, John F. Slavich, Joseph K. Taussig, J. Frank Taylor, and Earl Warren. Also included are letters from his son, John F. Greenslade, also a naval officer, written primarily between 1923 and 1936.
The Speeches and Writings series contains speeches and addresses on naval questions, command issues, and world affairs, with related correspondence, delivered between 1927 and 1948, articles on naval matters written between 1931 and 1944 for various publications, and theses and papers written at the Naval War College between 1925 and 1928.
The Subject File includes correspondence, dispatches, and memoranda which document Greenslade's tenure as chief officer of a commission to locate naval and air base sites in British possessions in 1940 and 1941. Files for each location include memoranda, charts, and aerial photographs. Correspondents in these files include William H. Beck, Stanley Truman Brooks, Edward, Duke of Windsor, Philip Henry Kerr, marquis of Lothian, Gordon J. Lethem, and Herbert Pott.
The Subject File also includes material related to the North Sea mine barrage and Greenslade's command of the mine layer Housatonic between 1918 and 1919. His personal and private diary from the Housatonic is found in the Diaries series. Other files include memoranda, correspondence, cables, and printed matter relative to naval operations, submarine force command issues, and the cruise of the collier Vulcan, which dealt with a dispute about the German ship Waltraute and payment for its cargo of coal in 1914-1915. Topics also include the Pacific Coast Joint Committee for Shipbuilding and Ship Repair, the Naval Shore Establishment Board, the United States Naval Academy, and the Naval War College, which Greenslade headed between 1926 and 1928.
The Subject File contains correspondence with John Reber concerning the "Reber Plan" for development of the San Francisco Bay area, Greenslade's résumé of service, correspondence and memoranda concerning Greenslade's duty status and disability retirement, and honors and decorations of both Greenslade and his son, John F. Greenslade. Other material includes a map and newspaper from Veracruz, Mexico, 1856-1957, typescripts of naval history documents, and correspondence relating to the donation of the Panton-Innerarity Papers, Florida history documents originally belonging to Greenslade's mother, to the Florida Historical Society.
The Miscellany includes photograph albums documenting official naval activities, specifically cruises of the Housatonic, cruiser Galveston, mine layer Shawmut, battleship Maryland, and others, the selection of base sites in British possessions, Greenslade's visit to the Kaiser Shipyards in Richmond, California, the Naval Proving Ground in Indian Head, Maryland, and the dedication of two ships by his third wife, Alma Greenslade. Three photograph albums, dated 1896-1933, including personal and family photographs, and a scrapbook of Greenslade's travel on the airship Hindenburg in 1936 have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division.
The Miscellany also includes assorted printed matter in the form of scrapbooks for the years 1895-1952, clippings about Greenslade, invitations, programs, proclamations, and a reading file of articles, monographs, and periodicals on military and foreign affairs.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is arranged in six series:
Diaries, 1895-1920
Correspondence, 1918-1949
Speeches and Writings, 1925-1948
Subject File, 1847-1957
Miscellany, 1888-1961
Oversize, 1847-1952
Container List
- Diaries, 1895-1920 (Box 1)
  Diaries, including some family correspondence and logs kept at the United States Naval Academy and on numerous vessels.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 1895-1900, United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., diary and letters (Box 1)
  - 1899-1903, Log, Chicago (cruiser), 1899-1901; reviewing cruise, Princeton (gunboat), 1901-1902; Solace (hospital ship), 1902, Texas (battleship), 1902-1903 (Box 1)
  - 1902-1904, service on Texas (battleship) (Box 1)
  - 1914, 1918-1920 Cruise of the Vulcan (collier), 1914; Housatonic (mine layer), 1918; Cole (destroyer), Baku trip, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, 1918-1949 (Box 1-2)
  General and family correspondence.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of correspondence and therein chronologically.
  - Administrative, 1928-1945 (Box 1)
  - Congratulation and sympathy letters, 1930-1948 (Box 1)
  - General, 1918-1947 (Box 1)
  - Greenslade, John F. (son) and family (Box 1)
    - 1923-1926 (Box 1)
    - 1927-1936, 1942-1949 (Box 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1925-1948 (Box 2-3)
  Speeches and writings.
  Arranged under the headings speeches and writings and therein alphabetically by type of material.
  - Speeches (Box 2)
    - Correspondence, 1931-1945 (Box 2)
    - Minor addresses, 1927-1932 (Box 2)
    - Texts (Box 2)
      - 1931-1944, (5 folders) (Box 2)
      - 1945-1948 (Box 3)
  - Writings (Box 3)
    - Articles (Box 3)
      - "Command, U.S. Navy," 1932 (Box 3)
      - Miscellany, 1931, 1941-1944 (Box 3)
      - "Navy Logistics: The Coordination of the Naval Logistic Effort on the Pacific Coast," 1944 (Box 3)
      - "One Year of War: Unity of Command Vital," 1943 (Box 3)
      - "Security of National Interests," 1935 (Box 3)
    - Theses and command studies, Naval War College, Newport, R.I., 1925-1928 (Box 3)
- Subject File, 1847-1957 (Box 3-7)
  Correspondence, memoranda, dispatches, printed matter, maps and charts, and photographs.
  Arranged alphabetically by topic and then chronologically.
  - Battles of Mexico, map, 1847 See Oversize (Box 3)
  - Free American, Veracruz, Mexico, 1847 See also Oversize (Box 3)
  - Greenslade, John F., naval service and commendations, 1943-1945, undated (Box 3)
  - Honors and decorations, 1928, 1937-1949 (Box 3)
  - Inactive duty status and disability, 1946-1949 (Box 3)
  - Institute of Pacific Relations, and World Affairs Council of Northern California, 1942-1949, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - Military orders and associations, memberships, 1905, 1940-1949 (Box 3)
  - Naval history typescripts, circa 1925-1934, 1939, undated (Box 3)
  - Naval operations, memoranda on, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
  - Naval Shore Establishment Board, 1940-1941 (Box 3)
  - Naval War College, Newport, R.I., 1928-1936 (Box 4)
  - Navy register, 1856 (Box 4)
  - North Sea mine barrage (Box 4)
    - General, 1918-1919, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Housatonic (miner layer), log extracts, 1918 (Box 4)
    - Printed matter, 1918-1919, 1938, 1946 (Box 4)
    - Track charts, 1917-1918 See Oversize (Box 4)
  - "Organization of the U.S. Naval Forces on Shore at Vera Cruz, Mexico," 1914 (Box 4)
  - Pacific Coast Joint Committee for Shipbuilding and Ship Repair, 1941-1943 (Box 4)
  - Panton-Innerarity Papers, donation to Florida Historical Society, 1938-1946, undated (Box 4)
  - Résumé of naval service, 1948 (Box 4)
  - San Francisco Bay, Calif., area development, Reber plan, 1942-1947 (Box 4)
  - San Francisco Committee on Foreign Relations, San Francisco, Calif., 1945 (Box 4)
  - Selection of base sites in British possessions (Box 4)
    - General (Box 4)
      - Correspondence (Box 4)
        - Employment, recommendations, sale of land, 1940-1941 (Box 4)
        - General, 1940-1941, undated (Box 4)
      - Dispatches, 1940, undated (Box 5)
      - Memoranda, 1940-1941, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5)
      - Photograph albums, 1940, (2 folders) (Box 5)
    - Location of base sites (Box 5)
      - Antigua, 1891, 1933, 1940-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 5)
      - Bahamas, 1938-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 5)
      - Bermuda, 1901, 1933, 1938-1941 See also Oversize, (2 folders) (Box 6)
      - British Guiana, 1924-1925, 1939-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
      - Jamaica, 1939-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
      - Martinique, 1929, 1936-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
      - Newfoundland (Box 6)
        - General, 1927, 1939-1941, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
        - Maps, photographs, printed matter, 1937-1940, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
      - St. Lucia, 1929, 1940, undated See also Oversize (Box 6)
      - Trinidad, 1930, 1939-1941, 1957, undated See also Oversize (Box 7)
  - Submarine force, fleet command issues, 1931-1936 (Box 7)
  - United Nations organization and problems, 1932, 1945 (Box 7)
  - United States Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md. (Box 7)
    - Examinations and marks, 1895-1899 (Box 7)
    - Printed matter, 1896-1946, (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Waltraute (ship) case, cruise of Vulcan (collier), 1914-1915, 1922 (Box 7)
- Miscellany, 1888-1961 (Box 7-11)
  Clippings and other printed matter, photograph albums, scrapbooks, and a reading file of articles and other publications.
  Arranged alphabetically by type of material and then chronologically.
  - Clippings about Greenslade, 1903, 1920-1950, undated (Box 7)
  - Invitations, programs, guest lists, 1919-1945, undated (Box 7)
  - Photograph albums (Box 8)
    - Housatonic (miner layer) and Galveston (cruiser) cruises, 1918-1919 (Box 8)
    - Naval Proving Ground, Indian Head, Md., 1920, (2 folders) (Box 8)
    - Shawmut (mine layer) cruise, 1923 (Box 8)
    - Maryland (battleship), Arizona (battleship) and others, 1937 (Box 9)
    - Kaiser Shipyards, Richmond, Calif., 1944 (Box 9)
    - Bronx (attack transport) launch, 1945 (Box 9)
    - Golden Rocket (stores ship) launch, 1945 (Box 9)
  - Proclamation, Golden Gate Bridge Festival, 1961 (Box 9)
  - Reading file on military and foreign affairs (Box 9)
    - Articles, four binders, 1925-1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 9, Box 10)
    - Monographs, 1941-1945 (Box 10)
    - Periodicals, 1943-1947 See Oversize (Box 10)
  - Report cards and high school graduation, Bellevue, Ohio, 1888-1895 (Box 10)
  - Scrapbooks (Box 10)
    - 1895-1928 (Box 10)
    - 1928-1941 See Oversize (Box 11)
    - 1937-1943 See Oversize (Box 11)
    - 1941-1943 See Oversize (Box 11)
    - 1942-1943 See Oversize (Box 11)
    - 1943-1946 See Oversize (Box 11)
    - 1943-1950 (Box 11)
    - 1944-1952 See Oversize (Box 11)
- Oversize, 1847-1952 (Box OV 1-OV 17)
  Oversize material consisting of photograph albums and periodicals.
  Arranged according to the series, folders, and boxes from which the items were removed.
  - Subject File (Box OV 1)
    - Battles of Mexico, map, 1847 (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
    - Free American, Veracruz, Mexico, 1847 (Container 3) (Box OV 1)
    - North Sea mine barrage (Box OV 1)
      - Track charts, 1917-1918 (Container 4) (Box OV 1)
    - Selection of base sites in British possessions (Box OV 2)
      - Location of base sites (Box OV 2)
        - Antigua, 1891, 1933, 1940 (Container 5) (Box OV 2)
        - Bahamas, 1938, undated (Container 5) (Box OV 3)
        - Bermuda, 1901, 1933, 1938-1941, undated (Container 6) (Box OV 4)
        - British Guiana, 1924-1925 (Container 6) (Box OV 5)
        - Jamaica, 1939-1940, undated (Container 6) (Box OV 6)
        - Martinique, 1929, 1936, n.d. (Container 6) (Box OV 7)
        - Newfoundland (Box OV 8)
          - General, 1927, 1939-1940, undated (Container 6) (Box OV 8)
          - Maps, photographs, printed matter, undated (Container 6) (Box OV 8)
        - St. Lucia, 1929, 1940, undated (Container 6) (Box OV 9)
        - Trinidad, 1930, 1940, undated (Container 7) (Box OV 10)
  - Miscellany (Box OV 11)
    - Reading file on military and foreign affairs (Box OV 11)
      - Periodicals, 1943-1947 (Container 10) (Box OV 11)
    - Scrapbooks (Box OV 12)
      - 1928-1941 (Container 11) (Box OV 12)
      - 1937-1943 (Container 11) (Box OV 13)
      - 1941-1943 (Container 11) (Box OV 14)
      - 1942-1943 (Container 11) (Box OV 15)
      - 1943-1946 (Container 11) (Box OV 16)
      - 1944-1952 (Container 11) (Box OV 17)